Ray Kirkpatrick papers, Inclusive: 1939-2000, undated; Bulk: 1945-1955
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Ray Kirkpatrick papers
Inclusive: 1939-2000, undated; Bulk: 1945-1955
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
28
Kirkpatrick, Ray, 1922 - 1998
2 document boxes, 1 oversize box
The Ray Kirkpatrick papers include certificates, diplomas, photographs, scrapbooks, news clippings, correspondence, and subject files. Items are inclusive of his time before, during, and after his service in the Texas House of Representatives.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Ernest Ray Kirkpatrick was born in Trenton, Fannin County, Texas, on July 9, 1922. He was a graduate of Trenton High School in 1940, and served in the United States Army from 1942-1945. His tour of duty included stops in Italy, France, and North Africa.
After his return home, Ray Kirkpatrick, a Democrat, was elected to represent the 41st District in the Texas House of Representatives. He represented this district during the 50th, 51st, and 52nd Legislatures from 1947 to 1952. Kirkpatrick served on several committees, including Contingent Expenses, Federal Relations, and Military and Veterans Affairs. He was also a member of the Appropriations Committee and appointed Chairman, a record-setting accomplishment reached at the age of 26.
Ray Kirkpatrick graduated from the Baylor School of Law in 1958, and held a private practice until 1963 when he joined the State Board of Insurance. He was active with the Masons, American Legion, and Veterans of Foreign Wars. Kirkpatrick died on November 3, 1998.
Scope and Content
The Ray Kirkpatrick papers include certificates, diplomas, photographs, scrapbooks, news clippings, correspondence, and subject files. Many items are personal in nature, however some of the topical items and photographs highlight the work he did while serving in the Texas House of Representatives. Also included are items documenting his time as a student at Baylor University, his business with the State Board of Insurance, and participation with the Masons.
Arrangement
An inventory was created for this collection in 2000 and included four series. These have been retained but renamed and organized to better describe the materials. The current arrangement is as follows: Certificates, News Clippings and Scrapbooks, Photographs, and Topical.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 28. Acquired 2000-01-28
Related Resources
Related references
“Ray Kirkpatrick.” Legislative Library of Texas. Accessed October 18, 2018.
“Ray Kirkpatrick.” Texas State Cemetery. Accessed October 18, 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Kirkpatrick, Ray,1922-1998DLArchives--Indexes.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University. Alumni Association.; Baylor University. Law School.; Freemasons--Texas.; Texas. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Texas. State Board of Insurance -- Officials and employees.; United States. Army.
Subjects
Greek letter societies -- Texas -- Waco.; Legislators -- Texas.; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States.
Genres
Albums (Books); Certificates.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Diplomas.; Photographs.; Records (Documents)
- Certificates, 1939-1984, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Certificates series contains documents related to Ray Kirkpatrick’s involvement in several state and local organizations from 1939-1984. Notable groups bestowing honors include the State Board of Insurance, Baylor Alumni Association, the Texas Legislature, and the Masons. His work on the Texas Civil War Centennial and participation in the Acacia and Rho Gamma Sigma fraternities is also recognized, as well as his appointments as Admiral of the Texas Navy and Commodore of the Brazos. This series is arranged chronologically and is in good condition.
  - General, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, Oversized, 1951-1981 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - General, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- News Clippings and Scrapbooks, 1946-1953, undated; 2
  The News Clippings and Scrapbook series is dated 1946-1953, and contains clippings from Ray Kirkpatrick’s tenure in the Texas Legislature. Due to the condition of the original Issues scrapbook, a research copy has been created and retained. A second scrapbook will be digitized and made available as part of the library digital collections. This series is arranged chronologically and in good condition.
  - General, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Issues Scrapbook, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 1948-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1943-1997, undated; 3
  The Photographs series is dated 1943-1997, and includes personal photographs as well as those acquired while on duty for the Texas Legislature. Several military photographs can be found along with autographed photos from Sam Rayburn, Speaker of the House Gib Lewis, and others. Kirkpatrick’s time with the State Board on Insurance is documented as well. This series is arranged chronologically and in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Banquet, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Group Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jack Brooks with Ray Kirkpatrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jerry Sadler with Ray Kirkpatrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Kirkpatrick in American Legion Hat, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sam Rayburn, Autographed, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Searcy Bracewell with Ray Kirkpatrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Speech by Waggoner Carr, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ray and Joyce Manford with military officer and Ray Kirkpatrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Waggoner Carr with Ray Kirkpatrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Military, circa 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ray Kirkpatrick, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Senator George Parkhouse, Autographed, 1959 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Appointment to State Board of Insurance, swearing in, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Preston Smith & Ray Kirkpatrick, Autographed, 1972 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - State Board Insurance Staff Services, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gib Lewis Autographed, 1985-1991 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - High school reunion, Class of 1939-1940, Trenton, Fannin Co., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Topical, 1943-2000, undated; 4
  The Topical series is dated 1943-2000, and includes pamphlets, membership cards, correspondence, military, personal, and legislative papers. Correspondence includes personal letters, constituent letters, and Dear Colleague letters. Military papers are from Kirkpatrick’s time in the Army as well as in the National Guard. This series is arranged alphabetically by topic and is in good condition.
  - Acacia Fraternity, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Affidavit of Loyalty, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Campaign Speech, handwritten, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Coin Club, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, Baylor, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, Constituents, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, Constituents, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, Constituents, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, Personal, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Personal Postcards, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Sam Rayburn, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dear Colleague Letters, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dear Colleague Letters, 1950-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Invitations and receptions, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Legislation, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Legislative Budget Board, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Masons, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Membership cards, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Military papers, U. S. Army (RESTRICTED), 1943-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Military papers, National Guard (RESTRICTED), 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Retirement, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - State Board of Insurance, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Speaker Candidacy, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Texas Civil War Centennial Commission, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Texas Legislature: resolution re death of father, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - University of Texas transcripts, 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Veteran’s Benefits, Personal, 1947-1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)